And so now we talk about quantization the q and q Laura.
이제 퀀타이즈 얘길 하죠 q&amp;q 로라
Q stands for quantized quantized.
Q는 퀀타이즈된 퀀타이즈죠
Laura.
로라예요
And I did mention quantization briefly, I believe in week three.
3주 차에 퀀타이즈를 잠깐 언급했었죠
So you may remember some of this.
그럼 기억날지도 모르겠네요
But now now we'll talk about it for reals.
이제 진짜 얘기를 해보죠
So here's the problem.
문제는 이거예요
The we're working with these smaller models, the 8 billion parameter version of llama 3.1.
우린 작은 모델로 작업하고 있어요 80억 매개 변수 버전의 llama 3이죠 1번요
And we've come up with this clever scheme that Laura for, for working with smaller dimensional matrices
이 기발한 계획도 로라가 생각해 냈어요 소차원 행렬을 연구하면 메모리를 더 많이
so that we can get more memory.
얻을 수 있죠 Get up
But the the problem is that even that base model, even the small version of it, the 8 billion version
그런데 문제는 기본 모델조차도 작은 버전이라도 80억 버전이라도
of it, will take up 32GB of Ram.
램 32GB를 쓴다는 거예요
That's, uh, 8 billion floating point numbers, which are each 32 bits long.
80억 개의 부동 소수점 수죠 각각 32비츠 길이로요
Uh, and so it's going to fill up a GPU.
GPU 안을 채울 거예요
In fact, the cheap GPUs that will be using on T4 boxes only have 15GB of memory in them, so it won't
T4 박스에 사용할 저렴한 GPU는 메모리가 15GB밖에 안 돼요 기본 모델
even fit the base model itself.
자체에도 맞지 않죠
We're going to be out of memory right away, so that is a problem.
메모리가 바로 바닥날 거예요 그게 문제죠
Lora is very useful in making things better for us, but it's not good enough because we can't even
로라는 우리에게 더 나은 환경을 만들어 주지만 베이스 모델 자체를 메모리에
fit the base model itself in memory.
넣을 수 없으니 충분하지 않아요
Because 8 billion might be a small size of a model in some worlds, but it's still an enormous number
80억이면 어떤 세계에선 작은 모형 크기일 수 있지만 그래도 엄청난 수의 매개 변수니까요
And so that that then gives us a challenge.
그래서 어려운 점이 많아요
So this quite surprising discovery was made.
그래서 이 놀라운 발견이 이루어졌죠
That is what we will be working with.
그게 우리가 작업할 거예요
And at first it sounds almost too good to be true.
처음에는 너무 좋아서 믿기 힘들 정도였죠
It sounds like this is a way to have your cake and eat it.
두 마리 토끼를 다 잡을 수 있는 방법 같네요
And it kind of is.
그런 셈이죠
So the, the idea that that, that some people had was, okay, so we've got 8 billion parameters.
그래서 어떤 사람들은 80억 개의 매개 변수가 있다고 했죠
If we try and have fewer parameters like we have a 4 billion parameter model, we lose a lot of the
40억 개의 매개 변수 모델처럼 적은 매개 변수를 가지려고 한다면 모델의 힘을
power of the model.
많이 잃게 돼요
Those 8 billion parameters give us lots of knobs to turn.
그 80억 개의 매개 변수 덕분에 돌릴 노브가 많아요
It's in this very clever architecture.
이 기발한 건축물에 그 점이 있어요
It gives us a lot of power.
큰 힘을 주죠
All right.
좋아요
So let's not cut down the number of parameters.
매개 변수의 수를 줄이지 말죠
Instead of doing that, let's just reduce the precision of each of these parameters.
그렇게 하는 대신 각 매개 변수의 정밀도를 낮추죠
It's like saying instead of being able to turn it through a very sort of finely grinded wheel, we're
곱게 갈린 바퀴를 통과하는 게 아니라 몇 가지 설정을 통해
going to make it go click, click, click, click through a few settings.
클릭, 클릭, 클릭하게 하는 거죠
Uh, and so that that was a thinking let's just reduce the precision of each of these weights but keep
그래서 생각한 건데 무게의 정밀도는 줄이고 무게의 개수는 그대로
the same number of weights.
두기로 했어요
Now you might think logically all right, but you're just cutting the amount of information.
논리적으로 생각할 수 있지만 정보의 양을 줄이고 있어요
Surely it's going to be if you have half the amount of information, it's going to be quite similar
정보가 절반만 있어도 무게의 수가 절반인
to having half the number of weights.
것과 비슷할 거예요
Uh, and it turns out that that's not the case.
알고 보니 그렇지 않더군요
For whatever reason, if you lower the precision, you do get some reduction in quality of the neural
어떤 이유에서든 정밀도를 낮추면 신경망의 질이 어느 정도 떨어지지만 생각만큼 떨어지진
network, but not as much as you might think.
않아요. Get it.
It still retains a lot of its power.
아직도 그 힘을 간직하고 있죠
And it turns out that this is just a great trick that allows you to fit bigger models in memory with
이건 메모리에 같은 수의 매개 변수로 더 큰 모델을 넣게 해주는 훌륭한
the same number of parameters.
트릭이에요
Just lower precision means that it takes up less memory.
정밀도가 낮으면 메모리 소모가 less예요
So it's surprising it works remarkably well.
놀라울 정도로 잘 작동하죠
And in fact, you could take the 32 bit floating point numbers that you normally have and reduce it
여러분이 평소에 가지고 있는 32비트 부동점 수를 취해서 8비트
all the way down to eight bit numbers, and you still get good performance.
숫자로 줄여도 여전히 좋은 성능을 낼 수 있어요.
And then and now this is where it starts to sound really crazy.
그리고 여기서부터 정말 미친 소리처럼 들리기 시작하죠
You can reduce it all the way down to four bits.
4분의 1로 줄일 수 있어요
So each number is just a four bit number.
각 숫자는 네 비트짜리 숫자죠
If you think of that from from an integer point of view, that it's as if each number is going from
정수의 관점에서 생각해 보면 각각의 숫자는 0에서
0 to 15 and that's it.
15까지밖에 없어요
Just just in whole numbers.
그냥 숫자만 따져서요
That's how low the precision is.
그 정도로 정확성이 낮죠
Like a click that just has has 16 settings on it.
클릭은 16개의 설정을 가지고 있어요
Um, and you still get pretty good performance.
그래도 여전히 좋은 연기를 보여줬어요 get it get it
Sure.
네
You do see a bit of a, of a drop in quality, but only a bit.
비트의 품질이 떨어지긴 했지만 아주 조금이에요
Um, and so this was the, the intuition.
그게 바로 직관이었어요
And this, of course, dramatically reduces the memory requirement and allows one to fit bigger models
이렇게 하면 메모리 요구 사항이 급격히 줄고 메모리에서 더 큰 모델에
in memory.
맞게 되죠
There are a couple of of minor technical details that I'll mention.
몇 가지 사소한 기술적인 사항을 언급할게요
One of them is that I just talked about the click switch.
그 중 하나는 방금 말씀드린 클릭 스위치예요
You can think of it as being like a number from 0 to 15.
0부터 15까지의 숫자로 생각해 보세요
Typically, it's in fact not interpreted as an integer, but as a four bits are used to to be considered
일반적으로 4비트는 정수로 해석되지 않지만 4비트는 세분성이
as as floating point numbers just with lower granularity.
낮은 부동점수로 간주되거든요
And you'll see that in reality in an example.
예제에서 실제로 그걸 보실 수 있어요
And the other thing to to point out, which is something I didn't understand early on when when color
또 하나 지적하고 싶은 건 색깔이 처음 나왔을 때
first came out, is that this is the quantizing the base model, but it's not quantizing the, the,
제가 이해 못 했던 건데요 이건 베이스 모델을 수량화하는 거지 로라 어댑터를
the, the Lora adapters, they will still be 32 bit floats as you will see.
수량화하는 게 아니에요 보다시피 여전히 32 비트 플로트죠
Um, so we're just talking about reducing the precision of the base model, this enormous great base
베이스모델의 정밀도를 줄이는 것에 대해 얘기하고 있어요 이 거대하고 훌륭한 베이스모델을
model so that we can fit it in memory.
메모리에 넣어야 해요
So that is cu Lora.
저게 쿠 로라예요
That's quantization.
그게 퀀타이즈예요
It's going to feel more real when we see it in the lab in just a second.
잠시 후 실험실에서 보면 더 진짜 같을 거예요
But first I want to talk to you about three important hyperparameters in the next video.
하지만 먼저 다음 비디오에서 중요한 하이퍼파라미터 세 가지를 말씀드릴게요